Jud?
祖德？
What?
什么？
Yer'd better get up.
你该起床了
The alarm's gone off, yer know.
闹钟已经响过了
Do you think I don't know?
你以为我不知道吗？
- Jud? - What?
祖德？什么？
- You'll be late. - Shut it.
你要迟到了 知道了
- Clock's not fast, yer know. - I said, shut it.
闹钟是准时的 我说别吵了
- Give over. That hurts! - Well, shut it, then.
起床了 到时间了！ 别吵
I'll tell me mam on you.
我要告诉妈妈了
Shut yer stinkin' mouth.
闭嘴
Oh, Christ!
哦 天啊！
- Set clock on for me, Jud. For seven. - Set it yerself.
给我调7点 祖德 你自己调吧
Go on, you're up.
调一下吧 你都起来了
Hands off cocks; on socks.
闹钟坏了 起床吧
You rotten sod! Just because you've to get up!
就是因为你要先起床 把我的美梦打破了
- Another few weeks, you'll be up with me. - I'll not.
再过几周 你就要同我一同起床了 我才不会
- Won't yer? - No, cos I'm not gonna work down the pit.
不会？因为我不要在矿井里上班
- Where are yer gonna work? - I don't know, but not down the pit.
你去哪上班？我不知道 但不会在矿井里
No. And have I to tell yer why?
不会是吧 要我 告诉你为什么吗？
For one thing, you've to be able to read and write before they set yer on.
那只有一个可能 除非你读好书
And they wouldn't have a weedy little twat like thee.
那样就不会要你这样一个小傻瓜
- Switch t'light out, then. - Switch it out yerself.
把灯关掉吧 自己关吧
- I thought you weren't coming. - Why? I'm not late, am I?
我以为你不来了 为什么？我没有迟到吧？
Very near.
刚刚好
- I nearly was, though. - What do yer mean?
就是正好嘛 你什么意思？
Our Jud, he's taken t'bike.
祖德骑走了自行车
- What you gonna do, then? - Walk it.
那你怎么办？走路了
- How long d'yer think that's gonna take? - It'll not take me long.
你认为你能坚持多久？ 那也要不了很久
There's a waiting list a mile long for that job. Good lads, too, most of 'em.
那要走很远的 好小子
- From up Firs Hill, round there. - I haven't let you down, have I?
要翻过福斯山 我没有让你去啊？
- Mornin'. - Mornin'. Not very promisin'.
早 早安 不是太守信用
- A bit on the nippy side as well, I think. - Aye.
我想是有一点 是啊
- 20 Players tipped, please. - Oh, right.
20个人的小费 哦 对啊
- I've not got 20. Will two tens do? - Yes. That'll be quite all right, thank you.
不是20吧 只是10的两倍而已
Thank you. Right. Cheerio.
对 你说得很对 谢谢
- Cheerio. Good mornin', sir. - Good mornin'.
- 好 早上好 老师 - 早上好
You know what they said when I took you on?
你知道他们刚才说什么吗？
"You'll have to keep yer eyes open now. He'll take yer breath if you're not careful. "
你要仔细看清楚 否则你就要吃大亏
- I haven't taken owt of yours yet, have I? - I haven't given you a chance, that's why.
我还没有替你做什么吧？ 那是因为我还没给你机会
You don't have to. I haven't been nicking for ages now.
也没必要 我已好几年 没这样挑人家的毛病了
- Ah, well, don't stand about all day. - I'm goin'.
不要整天站着 我就走
- How tha goin' on? - Not so bad.
怎么样？还不错
Get one of these. Better than walkin'.
有了这种车 总比走路好
Only just. I could go faster on a kid's scooter.
有单脚滑行车的话 我可以走得更快
Tha knows what I always say; third-class ridin's better than first-class walkin'.
那就是我常说的： 三等坐骑比一等走路快
Third-class ridin'? In that ramshack?
三等坐骑？摇摇欲坠吧？
Ramshack? This is one of best models t'dairy's got. Cheeky! Sithee tomorrow.
摇摇欲坠？操！这是 最好的车！再见吧
- Can only go 20 mile an hour, as it is. - Tha's got too much rattle, thee.
一小时只能走20英里 你真罗嗦
"Desperate Dan is stronger than all, but this opponent makes him fall. "
丹比谁都强壮 但他 的对手将其挫败
"- Right! Where do you want to fight? - Right here!"
“好！你想打哪儿？就这！”
"SKID."
“打滑”
"Down I go again! What's making me fall?"
“我又要下来了！怎么会这样？”
"Now's my chance to - jump on his chest!"
“我要将他胸部踏扁了！”
"THUD."
“砰”
"You won't catch me out this time, you braggart!"
“你这个牛皮王 这个时候别臭美！”
"A sock in the midriff will settle your game!"
“肚子上这一拳就可以将你搞定”
"SPLASH."
“喇“地一声
"What's this on my face? Why, it's grease!"
“脸上的是什么？这是 怎么回事 是油！”
"- Give me that tube back! - That's how he kept making me slip!"
“把管子还回给我！ 那就是我怎么会滑倒！”
"He was squirting invisible grease under my feet!"
“他在我脚下若无其事的喷油！”
"You dirty twister! It's time somebody taught you a lesson!"
“你这个卑鄙小人 是该教训你的时候了！”
"- Take that! - CRASH!"
“看好！砰的一声！”
"- Where did he end up? - In the middle of next week, Uncle Dan!"
“结果会怎样呢？下周再见 丹叔叔”
- Evenin'. - I told yer it wouldn't take me long.
晚上好 我说过不会太久的
What did you do? Throw 'em over the gates?
你各家各户都到过了吗？
- I know some short cuts ont' way back. - I'll bet you do! Over other folk's property.
我知道走近路回家 你肯定 我肯定会知道的！那边的人家很富有
How many times d'yer want tellin' where to put that bag?
我告诉你多少次了 袋子该放哪？
- Time is it? - Time you were at school.
几点了？到你上学的时间了
Is it that late?
是迟到了吗？
I wouldn't be your teacher for all the coal in Barnsley.
我可不是你的专职老师
Oh, Mr Porter! Watch it, Mr Porter.
哦 小心 珀特先生！
Yer clumsy young bugger! What yer tryin' to do? Kill me?
你这个小笨蛋！你想干 什么？想害我不成？
I lost me balance.
我差点摔倒了
I wouldn't put it past yer, either. I fair felt me heart go then.
我不会放过你 把我吓死了
Just sit down here and relax a couple o' minutes.
坐这休息一会儿
Are yer all right now?
现在没事了吧？
- I'm bloody champion! - I'll be off, then.
真把我吓坏了！ 那我要出去了
And don't be late tonight.
今晚不要迟到啊
- Allot? - Sir.
艾劳特？到
- Bowser?
柏塞？到
Bridges?
布里格斯？
- Absent, sir. - Absent, Bridges. Casper?
没有来 先生 布里格斯没来 卡士柏？
- Sir. - Clegg?
到 克里吉？
- Fisher?
到 费希？
German Bight.
德国曲线
- Did you say something? - I didn't mean to, sir.
你说什么？没什么 老师
Stand up, lad. What did you say?
站起来 你！你说什么？
- German Bight, sir. - He's daft, sir.
德国曲线 老师 他是个笨蛋 老师
- Is this your ridiculous idea of a joke? - No, sir.
这就是你玩笑的幽默吗？ 不是的 老师
- What is the idea, then? - When you said "Fisher", sir.
那是什么意思？你说“费希”时
- What about it? - Fisher. German Bight.
那怎么了？ 费希 那就是德国曲线
It's the shipping forecast, sir. Fisher. German Bight. Cromarty.
那就是意味着航行 “费希” 就是德国曲线 克劳默人
I like to hear it every night, sir. I like t'names.
我每天晚上都听 我喜欢这个名字 老师
So you thought you'd enlighten me and the class with your idiotic information?
所以你要告诉我 而且还要全班同学 都知道这个白痴般的话？
- No, sir. - Making a mess of my register.
不是的 老师 就是捣乱
- It just came out. - And so did you, Casper.
那只是凑巧 我想是的 卡士柏
Just come out from under a stone.
从石头底下冒出来的吧
I said, quiet!
安静！
Is anyone else absent besides Bridges and Fisher?
除了布里格斯和费希 还有别人缺席吗？
Any girls?
有女生缺席吗？
Right. Now, then, it's time you were off to assembly.
好 你们该去集合了
One row at a time. This one, stand.
马上排成一排 这个人 站起来
Move forward.
向前走
Pamela, you're talking. Cut it out.
德国佬 你在说什么 闭嘴
- Billy, what do yer mean, Germans bite? - I'm sick of hearin' about "Germans bite"!
比利 “德国狗”什么意思 你的话真恶心！
- Are yer comin' nestin' tomorrow? - Ar.
你明天会来纳斯廷吗？会
- What time? - About six.
几点？大约6点
Don't be late.
不要迟到
- Coming, Guth? - Where?
走 吉斯？去哪？
- Nestin'. - When?
纳斯廷 什么时候？
- Tomorrow. - What time?
明天 几点？
- About six. - Can't. Takin't'girlfriend to Sheffield.
大约几点 不去 要带女朋友去设费尔德
Excuses!
借口
What do you want at this time in the morning?
大清早的你干什么？
Get your Mac up.
叫麦克起床
Hey, he's fast asleep. I can't get him up at this time.
他睡得正香呢 我不能这个时候叫醒他
- Just get him up for me. - His father, he'll be down to yer.
就帮我把他叫醒 他爸会下来
I'm not bothered about his father. I want your MacDowall.
我不想打扰他爸 我找麦德华
- Bugger off, you little sod! - Get him up, will yer?
滚开 你这个小东西！ 叫他起来 好吗？
- I'm not gettin' him up. - He said I had to get him up.
我不会叫他起来的 他说过让我叫他起床
He's fast asleep and he's not goin', so just get off with yer.
他睡得正香 不会起来的 你走吧
- Now, then. What's tha doin'? - Nowt.
你在这干什么？ 没什么
Bugger off, then. It's private property.
走开 这是私人地方
- Can I get up to that kestrel's nest? - What kestrel's nest?
我可以上去拿那鹰窝吗？ 什么鹰窝？
- Up wall. - No nest up there, so off tha goes.
在那墙上面 那里 没有什么窝 快走开
There is. I've seen 'em come out.
有 我看见过它们出来
What will tha do? Take all its eggs?
那怎么样？ 把它的蛋拿走吗？
- They're young 'uns. - Nowt to go up for, then, is there?
他们都是雏鹰 不要上去 还不一定有呢
Can I come to t'bottom, then? Never seen a kestrel's nest before.
我可以上去吗？以前从没见过鹰窝
Come on, then.
那好吧
There it is. That big hole.
在那个大洞里
- It's nested there for donkey's years now. - And I never knew.
他们在那做窝已经几年了 我从没发现
- No, there's not many that does. - Been watchin' from t'wood there.
不 没有太多的鹰在那里 要树林里可以看见
Goes onto t'post, then hovers,
站在那根杆子上 然后又在盘旋
then swoops down onto t'prey, carries it off to t'young 'uns. Looks great.
然后猛地扑向食物 把食物带回喂小鹰 多棒啊
I've been gonna knock that wall down for ages.
我把墙弄倒已经好几年了
- What for? - It's dangerous. I won't let her play near.
为什么？太危险了 我不会让我女儿来这附近玩
- If I lived round here, I'd train a young 'un. - Would yer?
如果我住在附近 我会养一只小鹰 会吗？
Yer can train 'em.
你可以养
Do yer know how?
你知道怎么养吗？
- Do you know? - No. There's not many that does.
你知道吗？不知道 不是很多人养
They're hard to train. If they're not kept properly, it's criminal.
很难养 养得不好的话 那就是罪孽
- Do yer know anybody who's kept 'em? - One or two.
你知道有谁在养吗？ 知道一两个
But, er, they had to let 'em go because they're hard to train.
但 他们也要放它们走 因为很难饲养
Where can I find out about 'em, then?
在哪儿可以找到这方面的资料？
Well, probably t'public library. They'll have some books on 'em.
那 大概在图书馆吧 那有这方面的书籍
- Where's that? - Down int' city.
在哪里？在城里
Hey, are you a member?
嘿 你是会员吗？
- What do yer mean? - Are you a member of the library?
你什么意思？ 你图书馆的会员吗？
I don't know about that. I only want a book on falconry.
我不知道 我只想要一本 有关饲养老鹰的书
You have to be a member to take a book out.
你必须是会员才能带书走
- I only want one. - Have you filled one of these forms in?
我只要一本 你填了表吗？
- No. - You're not a member, then.
没有 那你不是会员
You'll have to take one of these home for your father to sign.
你要带一份回去给你爸签字
- Me dad's away. - You can wait till he comes back home.
我爸不在 你可以等他回来
- I don't mean that. I mean he's left home. - I see. Your mother'll have to sign it.
我是说我爸离开我们家 我知道了 你妈也可以签
Ar, but she's at work and she'll not be home till tea time.
她要上班 要到喝下午茶时她才回来
There's no rush, is there?
那也不急 是吗？
I've never broke a book. I haven't tore it, or...
我不会损坏这书
Look at your hands. They're filthy. We'll end up with dirty books that way.
看看你的手 很脏啊 要把书弄脏了
- I don't ready dirty books. - I hope you don't. You're not old enough.
我不是有意的 我希望你不是 你还小
Me mam knows someone who works here. That'll help, won't it?
我妈认识在这上班 的人 那也不行吗？
No, not at all. You still have to have the back signed.
不 那根是本没用 你还是要回去签好字
To be a member, you'll have to have somebody over 21
要成为会员 必须年满21岁
who is on the borough electoral roll to sign it.
且必须是本区居民
- I'm over 21. - You're not over 21.
我有21岁 你没有
- Ar, but I vote. - You don't vote. You're not...
但我有选举权 你没有 你不是…
I vote for me mam. She dun't like votin', so I do it.
我代替我妈 她不喜欢 选举 所以我代替她
- Just have to wait for it, won't you? - Where would I find a book? In a shop?
还是要等 不是吗？我 在哪里可以找到这书？在书店吗？
You'd have to go down the street. There's a second-hand bookshop there.
你要上街去 街上可能有二手书店
- Hello. Can I help you? - Yes.
你好 能为你效劳吗？好
I'm rather interested in No雔 Coward's autobiography, Present Indicative.
我想要一本《诺尔·考沃德》的自传 要最新版的
- What's tha got this for? Tha can't read. - Give us it here.
你要这干什么？ 你又用不到 还给我
Get off! Falconry? What's tha want to know about falconry?
别吵！饲养老鹰？ 你看这书干什么？
Give it here!
还给我！
- Where've yer got this from? - I've lent it.
从哪来的？借的
Stole it, more like. Where've yer got it from?
偷的吧 从哪来的？
A shop in town.
城里的书店里
You must be crackers. I could understand if it were money, but chuff me, not a book!
你还真是个贼 偷钱还可以理解 难以相信的是竟是为了一本书
Have it!
拿去！
Look what yer've done. I'm lookin' after this book.
看看你在干什么 小心我的书
- And what better off will yer be? - A lot. I'm gonna get a kestrel and train it.
那有什么用？用处可大了 我要饲养一只鹰
Train it? Yer couldn't train a flea.
养鹰？你还养不活一只跳蚤
Anyway, where yer gonna get a kestrel from?
再说 从哪来的鹰？
- I know a nest. - Yer don't.
我知道有个窝 你哪儿知道
- All right, then, I don't. - Where?
好了 我不知道 在哪儿？
- I'm not tellin'. - I said, where?
我不告诉你 在哪儿里？
- You're hurtin' me arm! - Where, then?
你扭痛了我的手！在哪儿？
Monastery Farm.
蒙纳斯特 农场
Yer could have broke me arm then.
你伤了我的胳膊
I'll have to see about goin' round there wi' me gun.
我要拿我的枪去看看
- I'll tell t'farmer on yer. - Why? What's he got to do with it?
那的农场主在那 他在那干什么？
- He protects 'em. - Protects 'em?
他在那保护它们 保护它们？
Hawks are a menace to farmers. They eat all the poultry an' that.
老鹰是农场主的敌人 它会吃家禽
Ar, I know. They dive down onto t'cows and take 'em away.
我知道 它们会猛地扑向食物 然后就带走
- Funny bugger. - Well, yer talk daft. They're only small.
真滑稽 你才笨 他们还是雏鹰
They eat mice, insects, and little birds sometimes.
他们吃稻谷 昆虫 有时是小鸟
Hope I'll be watchin' a bird tonight. She'll not have feathers. Not all over, anyway.
希望我今晚能看到小鸟 她没有羽毛 也不是到处没有
- Have you had any tea yet, Billy? - No.
你喝过茶了吗 比利？没有
Well, get some, then. You where t'pantry is.
那去拿一些 再那食品室里
- How's yer horses gone on, Jud? - Not bad. Two winners.
你赛马怎么样 祖德？ 不坏 两个赢了
You haven't. Might be gettin' tret tonight, then.
那可没有过的 可能今晚可以得甜头
- Oh, somebody treats you every night. - Shut it!
每晚都有人这样招待你 闭嘴！
And don't you be comin' home blind drunk again, Jud.
不要再醉酒后回来啊 祖德
- Why? Are yer entertainin'? - You're kiddin'.
为什么？你要招待客人吗？ 开玩笑
If I entertained as much as you, I shall do all right, shan't I?
如果我可以象那样招待客人的话 那就好 不是吗？
What tripe you've been goin' out with lately. My God!
最近你们出去做些什么啊 天啊！
- Better'n that cripple you bring home. - What cripple? Reg? He's not a cripple.
最好带那个跋子回家 什么跋子？是莱格吗？他不是跋子
Will be if he comes in here tonight. At least them I go out with are not tightfisted.
今晚他来了的话就会
Who is? You chuck your bloody money around like a Scotchman with no arms!
至少我同他们出去不会那样吝啬 说谁呀？你花钱就象是一个没手的苏格兰人！
Have to use a spanner to get a threepenny bit out of his hand.
要他三便士出斤 都是要数了又数
Aye, because he's comin' wise to you.
那是因为他对你很精明
Listen, what about him you're goin' wi'? Tight as a camel's arse in a sandstorm.
那你觉得他怎么样？就象 沙漠风暴中的骆驼那样吝啬
Keep yer hand over yer mouth talkin' about him, cos yer'll get into trouble.
你住嘴 否则你就麻烦了
- You're not too big for a hidin'. - He can't do it.
这样还来得及 他不敢怎么样
Who can't? You might find that he's bigger than what you think.
谁不敢？你会发现他 比你想象的更壮大
More chance of gettin' struck by lightnin'.
这更容易遭雷劈
Shut yer face. I'm fed up of it. It's every Saturday night. I get ready, you're at me.
住嘴 我听够了 在每周六晚上 我想好了 你跟着我
And I always go out in a bloomin' mess and all upset.
我一般都去那些花红酒绿的地方 那里让我不安
Gettin' too big for yer boots, thinking you own t'house.
你的鞋子够亮了 想想你还没有成家
You don't own it yet, yer know.
你没有成家 知道吗？
- No. I will do one day, though, won't I? - Over my dead body.
终有一天我会的 要等我死后
- That's what I says, I'll own it one day. - I'm sick on it, Jud. I am, pig sick.
我只是说会有一天 祖德 我是一直盼著这一天
I work every day, and every Saturday night I go for a drink and you upset me.
我每天工作 每周六晚上我去喝酒 你就让我觉得不安
- I don't think I'll go, I'm that fed up. - I'll not miss yer.
我不去了 我受够了 我没有叫你不要去
You'll not miss nowt, will you? You'll be out there.
你也不会叫我不要去 是吗？你不在那
- Yeah. - Aye.
是的 对
By, what a smart-lookin' kid int' mirror. Some bird's gonna be lucky tonight.
镜中看来还挺帅的 今晚不知碰上哪只幸运的鸟
Listen to God's gift to woman.
记住女人钟爱的礼物
Fancy buying me a brandy and pep tonight?
今晚想给我买些白兰地和兴奋剂吗？
Aye. Hope it keeps fine for yer.
那希望你会喜欢
These could have done with a bit of a polish.
这些擦亮一下就好了
Still, never mind, it's gonna be dark soon.
不要紧 不久后会变暗的
What you gonna do with yerself tonight, love?
今晚你做什么 宝贝？
Read me book.
读书
Oh, look at t'time. Five to seven. I'm gonna be late again.
看看时间 差5分7点 我又要迟到了
Listen, Billy, there's two bob here. Chuck?
比利 这有两块钱 放在这好吗？
Get yerself some pop and some crisps. D'yer hear?
你自己去买些汽水和薯条 听见了吗？
Yeah.
嗯
- And don't still be up when I come in. - No.
- 在我回来之前不要走啊 - 不会
G'night, then.
晚安
Folks, thank you.
谢谢大家
Now a Tremeloes number.
一个大数字
Yer can have a good time up to a point,
那正是时候
but there comes a time when you want to settle down.
只要你想的话机会就来了
I'm gettin' a bit fed up of workin' all t'time.
我一直工作也受够了
There's plenty of time to settle down, in't there?
时间多得是 不是吗？
Depends what yer lookin' for, dun't it?
那要看你找什么样的 不对吗？
I just like to come home, get me meal, get a bath, change and out, me.
我只想回去吃一顿 洗 个澡 彻底洗一番
Not a care int' world.
不要想得太多
When you've been married once and yer marry a wrong 'un,
你一旦结了婚且婚姻不如意
it makes yer a bit apprehensive towards gettin'...
那会让你会懂得很多…
Well, you know, don't yer? Cos he were never good.
你知道的 不是吗？因为他也不是太优秀
But it makes yer a bit more wary about gettin' married again.
这就要求你要在结婚方面更加警惕
If she wants to go with a different bloke, it's not up to me.
如果她要找一个与众不同的人 那就不适合我
She's old enough to know her own mind.
她应该足够了解她自己
- Well, yeah... - .. settle down.
那…定下来
You can never tell with Billy. I sit and wonder sometimes what he will do.
你可以从不跟比利说 下我坐来有时就会想他会是怎么样
Perhaps if he had been brought up in a different environment
如果他在一个与众不同的环境中长大的话
and had a better education, he would have made more than what he has.
他会受到更好的教育 他会比现在更优秀
At the moment, he's hopeless. He's a hopeless case, in't he?
在那时 他就毫无希望 不是吗？
I'm happy as I am. I doubt if I could be any happier.
我目前活得很开心 我在想我或许活得更好
My lads have got nowt. I don't know what they're gonna do.
我小孩什么也没有 我不知道他们会怎么样
I don't know whether our Jud wanted to be a miner.
我不知道祖德是否想做一名矿工
From my point of view, Reg, when a woman gets to my age, you've two kids,
在我看来 莱格 一个个女人 到了我这年龄 你有两个小孩
you want to be settlin' down wi' a nice house
你要是安排好的话 那会有一个很好的家
and somebody to come home to yer, and be lookin' after 'em.
有人来到你家 可以帮你照看小孩
- Like I look after you. - Ar, but you're not married to me.
就象照顾你一样 但你不愿和我结婚
- Never mind. Giz a kiss. - Don't be so damned daft!
不要担心 来亲一下 别那样！
- He's had too much ale again. - I haven't.
你又喝多了 没有
- Yer have.
你就是 没有
Say, Mam, have you brought that cripple wi' yer?
妈 你带那个跋子来了吗？
Keep it shut. Keep it shut.
闭嘴
Keep it shut, all right?
住嘴 好吗？
Say, did everybody hear about him when he got married?
有人知道他什么时候结婚的吗？
He got confetti on elastic. That's how tightfisted he is.
他结婚那天 五彩纸屑有弹力后 才漫天飞舞 可见他有多小气
If he wants trouble, I'll give him trouble.
如果他想惹麻烦 他会让他麻烦
Billy, are tha asleep?
比利 你睡了吗？
Bleedin' things.
出血
Now, Billy!
比利！
- Give over. - Billy!
别吵 比利！
Help me get these bleedin' trousers off.
帮我把这些占了血的裤子拿开
Come on! Don't be all bleedin' night.
快点！不要让我整晚都流血
I'm fed up with this bloody game.
看到流血真是恶心
It's every Saturday night alike.
每周六都是这个样子
Don't help, will tha?
好了吧
Get back to sleep, yer... pig.
回来就睡 你这条猪
Hog. Sow.
肥猪 大母猪
Yer drunken bastard.
你这个醉鬼
Tha dun't like bein' called a bastard, does tha? Yer bastard!
看来又不象个讨厌鬼 是吗？你这个家伙！
Yer pig.
你这头猪
Pig.
猪
Hog.
肥猪
Sow.
大母猪
Drunken... bastard.
醉鬼
Bastard. Bastard.
死家伙
Drunken... pig.
醉猪
Pig.
猪
Billy! Billy!
比利！
"Three good meals a day I'll give him for about a fortnight. "
一日有丰盛的三顿 我要大约喂它两周
"If a piece of meat held between the finger and thumb of the gloved hand
“肉放在戴有手套的 母指和食指中间
is offered to the hawk, it will probably bend down and pull at it with its beak. "
把肉送到小鹰嘴边”
C'mon.
来啊
"As soon as the hawk will come a leash length indoors,
不久在小鹰脚上 系了一小段绳子
she may be tried off a fence or gatepost out of doors. "
它想尽力逃离笼中世界
"It is quite likely that although she was coming to the fist promptly indoors,
那也情有可原 因为它 不是生活在室内的世界
she will now refuse to come at all. "
它根本不想来的
"She will stand looking around her and ignoring the meat and fist in front of her. "
它朝自己四周看了看 根本不理它面前的食物
"When she will come a leash length outside,
当它能飞出这根绳子远时
she can be called greater distances by means of a creance,
那可以说飞得很远了
a long cord which is attached to the hawk to prevent her escaping. "
因为有根绳子系在 它脚上怕它飞走
"With luck, she will not attempt to fly away. "
还好 他不会再想飞走了
Come on, then.
过来
Kes! Tck, tck, tck, tck, tck.
凯斯！
Tck, tck, tck, tck, tck. Come on, lass.
过来 宝贝
Tck, tck, tck, tck, tck.
过来 凯斯！
Come on, Kes! Tck, tck, tck, tck, tck.
来
Come on, boys, get ready!
孩子们 快准备好！
Get ready now, you.
你 准备好
Skiving again, Guthrie.
又在磨蹭什么 嘉塞
No, sir. Mr Farthing has been talking to me.
没什么 老师 珐辛先生跟我讲话了
I'll bet that was stimulating for him, wasn't it, lad?
我想那一定是很刺激的 不是吗 小东西？
- What does that mean, sir? - The conversation. What do you think?
什么意思 先生？是谈话 你在想什么？
Does it mean "stimulate", sir?
你不是说很“很刺激”吗？
Stimulating, you fool! S- t-i-m-i-I-a-t-i-n-g. Stimulating.
很刺激 你这笨蛋！ 是S.T.I.M.U.L.A.T.I.N.G 刺激
Come on, get ready. You're two weeks late already.
好了 快点准备 你已两期迟到了
You three, get down, before I come and put yer down.
你们三个 快点给我下来
Casper, what d'you think you're doing? Get down. Why aren't you changed?
卡士柏 你在想什么？ 下来 为什么还没有换衣服？
- I've no kit, sir. - Casper, you make me sick.
我没有这些用具 先生 卡士柏 你真让我恶心
Every lesson it's the same old story, "Please, sir, I've no kit, sir. "
每堂课都是这样的话 老师 我真得没器具
Every lesson for four years, you've begged, borrowed, skived and scrounged.
上了四年的课了 你都是 在问人讨啊 借啊 偷偷摸摸的
Why is it, Casper, when all this lot can provide kit, you can't?
为什么 卡士柏 大家都有 只有你没有？
Don't know. Me mam says it's a waste of money now I'm leavin'.
不知道 我妈说我 现在离开的是浪费钱
You haven't been leaving the past four years, have you?
过去四年你都没有离开过 是吗？
No, sir.
是的 老师
- Use your spending money. - Don't like football, sir.
花点钱吧 不要花在 足球上 老师
- What's that got to do with it, Casper? - Don't know.
那怎么办 卡士柏？我不知道
- Anyway, I don't get enough. - Get a job, then, lad. Get a job.
总之 我没那么多钱 找份工作吧 小家伙
- I've got one, sir. - They pay you, don't they?
我已经找了 他们付你工资了吧？
Yeah, but I have to give it to me mam. I'm payin' me fines, like...
付了 但我要交给我妈 我要交罚金 比如…
You should keep out of trouble, lad! Keep out of trouble.
你不能这样了 小家伙 你不能再这样下去了
- I haven't bin in trouble since last time. - I'll get you some kit, Casper.
从上次开始 我就没 不再陷入麻烦中了
- Tha's had it now, Casper. - Shut thi mouth!
我会给你弄些器具 卡士柏 现在有了 卡士柏 闭嘴！
Right, Casper. Get into those.
好了 卡士柏 拿那些去
- They'll not fit me. - You can get into them, can't you?
我穿不了 你可以穿的 不能吗？
Yes, sir.
是的 先生
They'll keep your cobblers warm, Casper.
穿上后会让你这个皮匠更暖 卡士柏
- Take your vest and underpants off. - Don't wear 'em, sir.
把内衣裤脱掉 没有穿 老师
Casper, tuck 'em in. Thi privates are showin'.
卡士柏 把小弟弟藏好 要不会露出来
The muscleman o't'year!
有要射手在哦！
- He's just come back from Biafra. - Pull them up, Casper!
他刚从比夫拉回来 提起来 卡士柏！
- Pull them up! - Like that, sir?
提起来！是那样吗 老师？
Pull them down, Casper.
放下一点
You're too daft to laugh at.
你真的傻得没药可救了
Right. They'll do there.
好了 就这样
You lot, come on, get changed. Wasted enough time already.
你们 去 换好衣服 已浪费够多时间了
I'll give you a sample of my footballing skills.
我要教你们一些简单的足球技艺
A rare delight.
非常高兴才对
Watch yourself, Casper!
小心 卡士柏！
I won't tell you again, Crossland!
我不会再跟你讲了 克劳斯兰德！
Come on, move.
跑啊
Off that goal post!
给我下来！
Off that goal post. I'll be up there in a minute!
下来 我马上就要来了！
Come here, Tibbut. We'll pick two teams. You're the captain.
过来 迪柏特 我们分两队 你是队长
Right, line up on the halfway line, quickly.
好了 在半腰线上排好队 快点
- I'll have first pick. Paget. - That's not fair. You'll get t'best players.
我首先挑人 佩杰特
D'you wanna play football, or d'you wanna do some maths?
那不公平 你只挑好的球员
Paget, then. Come here.
你想踢足球还是在做数学题？
- Speed. - Walker.
佩杰特 到这来
- Clark. - Crossland.
斯皮德？沃克
- Kelsey. - Rowe.
克拉克 克劳斯兰德
Er... Clegg.
克里吉...先生
Bloody hell, I'm frozen already.
天啊 冻死人
- Joyce. - Birkinshaw.
乔伊斯 柏金萨
- Ryder. - Parker.
莱德 帕克
- Norton. - Come on, Parker.
诺顿 帕特 过来
Casper, I've got to have yer. Come on.
卡士柏 我就不得不选你了 过来
Don't act the goat. Come on, put 'em round your waist.
不要穿那件衣服 穿你的背心
Now.
好了
Right, we'll play with the wind, downhill, this way.
我们要这样挺直腰板 与寒冷作斗争
Paget, you're inside right. Come on.
佩杰特 你带队 走
- Who are you today, sir? Liverpool? - Don't you know your club colours?
你今天是哪个队啊？老师？利物浦队吗？ 你知道你们俱乐部的颜色吗？
- Manchester United, this. - Are you playing Denis Law, striker?
这是曼联队队服 你在扮演丹尼斯·劳的前锋角色吗？
No. Charlton today, lad. All over the field. Too cold for striker.
不 今天是扮演卡尔顿 小伙子 这整片草地对前锋来说都非常冷
Charlton's not as quick ont' turn as Law, is he?
卡尔顿的反应速度没有劳快 是吗？
- You tryin' to tell me about football? - No. I...
你想跟我讲足球？不是 我…
You trying to tell me? Anyway, Denis Law's in the wash this week.
你是想告诉我？ 丹尼斯·劳在本周被刷出去了
- Nobody's in goal, sir. - No goalie, sir.
没有人守门 老师 没有守门员 老师
- Who's in the goals? - Casper.
谁来守门？ 卡士柏
- Casper, what position are you playing? - Don't know, sir. Inside left?
卡士柏 你在什么位置？ 不知道 是左内线吗？
How can you be inside left back there, idiot? In the goals.
你怎么可以回到左内线 傻瓜？ 在球门
- I can't... - Now's your chance to learn. In the goals.
我不能…现在你的任务是学习 到球门去
Quick about it.
快点
- We're Manchester United. Who are you? - Spurs, then there's no clash of colours.
我们是曼联队 你们呢？ 斯普斯 那没有队服颜色冲突
Right, then, it's Manchester United versus Spurs in this cup tie here at Old Trafford.
那就是曼联与斯普斯 在老特拉福德举行的优胜杯决赛
And it's the fair-haired, slightly balding Charlton to kick off.
现由金发的 稍微有点 秃头的卡尔顿中线发球
Come on, Speed. What you playin' at, lad?
看好 斯皮德 你在那干什么 家伙？
Yer should be on the move, lad. It was at yer feet!
你要跑起来 小家伙 球就在你脚下！
Cross it, Ryder. Quickly.
带球 莱德 快点
Where's t'rest of my team?
我们队其他的人呢？
Come on, quickly, Casper. I've never seen such slack work in my life.
快点 卡士柏 我可从来 没见过那样的懒散法
- What's that for, sir? - Slack work, lad. Slack work.
怎么了 老师？太懒散
Hit that ball up the field, Parker.
帕克 把球踢远
I have to keep this shirt on after.
等会儿我还要穿这件衬衫
Cross the ball!
传球！
And Charlton goes through, and...
卡尔顿过人…
Oh, never! Never!
哦 怎么会！
- Penalty! - Never.
佩纳特！不会了
Who do you think you are? Bremner?
你以为你是谁？布里诺吗？
- Penalty. - No, it weren't, sir!
佩纳特 算了 老师 他不是有意的！
Outside that semicircle.
外围半圆
- Shall I take it, sir? - I take the penalties on this team.
是我发球吗 老师？ 我要给颜色给这个队看看
No one moves till this ball's kicked.
球一跑出后大家就跑？
Just watch this, Guthrie. Right, Clegg?
看好 嘉塞 克里吉？
You moved. You moved. Put it back.
你动了 把球拿回来
Penalty.
佩纳特
Behind the 18-yard line.
站到18码远的线外
Tha better save it, Cleggy! Else I'll drop tha.
最好守稳一点 克里吉丫！ 否则我就会进球
- He moved! - I didn't move, sir.
他走动了！我不能动 老师
The referee's decision is final.
一切听裁判的
- You should have done it the first time. - And that, boys, is how to take a penalty.
你第一次就应该进了 那就是惩罚 孩子们
Look one way and kick the other.
盯好人 一个跟一个
Come on, Tibbut, lad.
来 迪柏特
And Bobby Charlton has equalised for Manchester United,
波比 卡尔顿使曼联队将比分扳平
and the score is one goal each.
双方各有一次射门
That fat twat! He wants bleedin' milkin'. That big fat git!
肥猪！他想吮奶 大笨蛋
What did you say? What did you say?
你说什么？
- Nowt, sir. - Get off! In that changin' room! Get off!
没什么 老师下去！把衣服换了！
- I didn't say nowt, sir. - Off!
我没说什么 老师。 下去！
- I won't tolerate that on a football pitch. - That's our captain, sir.
在足球赛场上我不能允许有那样的现象发生 那是我们的队长 老师
I don't care who he is. You play this game like gentlemen.
不管你是谁 踢球就得文明
Right inside!
直接进去！
An early bath for you, lad.
早就为你准备好了水洗澡
- I'll bounce the ball up. - It's not fair! They never get sent off!
我来发球 那不公平！ 他们从没守过门！
- I shall be up there in a minute! - They never get sent off, sir.
我马上会回来！他们守不住门
Off!
走开！
What d'you think you two are doing?
你们两个在干什么？
- What are you doing? - Practising, sir.
你们两个在干什么？热身
Show me what you're doing.
告诉我你们在干什么
Casper!
卡士柏！
Casper, what do you think you are, lad? An ape?
卡士柏！你以为你是谁 嗯？是猿猴吗？
- All he needs now is a banana. - Get down. I'll make you red hot.
他现在要的是香蕉
Thank you. Now, for my next trick...
下来 否则我要给你红牌了
I'll show you a trick! Get back in that goal!
谢谢大家 下一个表演是…
- What's up? - That hurt. That ball, it's hard as iron.
我会给你表演！ 给我回到球门中去！
Ar, I know. It's like a stone, innit?
怎么了？受伤了 那球 象铁一样硬
- I'm bloody freezin'. - My feet are like blocks o' ice.
我知道 象石头一样 是吗？ 血都冻僵了 我的脚象冰一样的
Me knees, look at 'em. They're goin' pale.
我的膝盖 看看 变得灰白了
Look at t'colour. It's gone white.
看看颜色都变白了
Oh, I wish I'd brought a note.
早知有本笔记就好
- Great goal, that, sir. - I'll give yer "great goal", lad.
那是漂亮射门 老师 我会给你们一个漂亮射门 小伙子
- Spurs into the sixth round of t'Cup. - Sixth round? I'll give you six of the best.
斯普斯进入了第六轮比赛 第六轮？我会给你六个最好的进球
- Lost again, sir? - Fetch my tracksuit.
再丢几球吧 拿我的运动服来
- Better luck next time. - Disgusting!
祝下次好运 真恶心
- In a hurry, Casper? - I have to get home, sir.
走那么快干吗 卡士柏？ 我要回家了 老师
- Really? - Yes, sir.
真的吗？是的
- Forgotten something? - No, sir.
忘了什么没有？没有
- Are you sure? - Yes, sir.
真的吗？ 是的
- What about the showers? - I've had one, sir.
洗过澡了吗？ 洗过了
- You can ask any of 'em, sir. - I'll just do that.
你可以问他们 我刚洗过
- Have you seen him have a shower? - No, sir.
你看见他洗澡了吗？ 没有
- Have you?
你呢？
- Have you seen him have a shower? - Who, sir?
你看见了 他洗澡吗？ 哪一个呀 老师？
- Casper. - When, sir?
卡士柏 什么时候 老师？
- Just now. Has he had a shower? - Had a shower, sir?
刚才 他洗过了吗？ 你洗了吗？ 老师？
Has Casper had a shower?
卡士柏洗过澡了吗？
What you fooling about at, lad?
你开什么玩笑？
- I don't think so, sir. - Speed, you'll get what Casper just had.
我想没有 斯皮德 那你知道卡士柏刚才做了什么
No one's seen you have a shower, Casper. Cos you haven't had one.
没有人看见你洗了澡 因为你没洗
- Me mam says I ain't to have a shower. - Come here. What's your mother say?
我妈说我不要洗澡 过来 你妈说什么好了？
I ain't to have a shower, sir. I've got a cold.
我不应洗澡 老师 因为我感冒了
- Where's your note, then? - Can I bring it this afternoon, sir?
你的笔记在哪里？ 我今天下午带来 行吗？
That's no good, lad. I want one now.
不好 我现在想要
Any boy wishing to be excused physical education, or showers,
每个孩子都想为体育 课或者洗澡找借口
must, at the time of the lesson, produce a sealed letter of explanation
上课时就拿一些的解说信来
signed by one of his parents or his legal guardian.
上面还有家长或 合法保护人的签名
- Go on, sir, let me go home. - You can go, lad.
好了 老师 让我回家吧 你可以走
Hey, come here. When you've had a shower.
嘿 过来 去洗个澡
- I haven't a towel, sir. - Borrow one.
我没毛巾 借一条
- Nobody'll lend me one. - Have a drip-dry, then. Shower, come on.
没人会借给我 那就这样洗吧 去
- MacDowall. - Sir?
麦克多沃尔 老师你叫我？
Come here, lad.
过来
Come here. What's this?
过来 这是什么？
Our dog did it, sir.
家里的狗弄的
- Your dog did it? - Aye.
你的狗弄的 是的
It bit me while I were fightin' it last night.
昨晚我打它时它就咬我
A dog wearing nylons, lads.
穿著尼龙衣的狗
Bloody heck!
天啊！
- Still in a hurry? - Can I go now, sir?
还急吗？我可以走了吗 老师？
- Have a proper wash. - I've had one, sir.
好好地洗 洗过了
- In the shower, lad. In the shower. - I've got to get home.
到水龙头下去 我要回家了
In the shower.
到水龙头下去
Ryder, Speed, come here.
莱德 斯皮德 过来
Yes, you two. Come on.
对 你们两个 过来
Stay here and see that he doesn't come out.
站在这看好他
- Do what, sir? - I said, stay there.
干什么 老师？我说站到这
See that he doesn't come out.
且看好他
Agh! Sir! It's gone cold!
老师！好冷啊！
Got a sweat on, Casper? I thought you might need a cooler after your exertions.
出汗了吗 卡士柏？ 我想你运动后得冷却一下
It's not right, sir. I'll catch me death of cold in here. It's not right.
不是的 老师 我会冻死在这里的
Was it right when you let that goal in deliberately?
是你故意放走那头羊的吗？
- Can't we go for us dinners? - No, you can stay there.
我们可以去吃饭了吗？ 不行 你们得站在那儿
- We're servers. - I don't care. They can serve themselves.
我们是服务生 我不管 他们可以自己照顾自己
You shouldn't put me in goal. You know I'm useless.
你不应该把我当作目标 我是没有用的
Now's your chance to learn.
现在你有机会学习了
Shall we let him out, sir? He'll catch his death of cold.
老师 可以放出他来吗？ 他这样会被冻死的
- He'll catch pneumonia. - I don't care what he gets.
他会得肺炎的 我不管他会得什么
If he thinks I'm running my blood to water for 90 minutes,
如果他觉得我可以 在水里泡90分钟的话
for him to deliberately throw the game away, he's got another think coming.
对他来说这个游戏就玩完 他又会想出其他的点子
Sir, we've got to go for us dinner.
老师 我们真的应该去吃饭了
- Get down! - He looks like a bleedin' snake!
下去！他好像条出血的蛇！
Think yourself lucky.
这次算你走运！
- 'Ey up, Jud. How yer doin'? - Rough, man.
老兄 你还好吧？很不爽 老兄
Why? You should be on top of the world on a day like today.
怎么啦？今天这样的日子 你应该是世界上最快乐的人
Another ten minutes and I'll be at t'bottom of it.
再过10分钟 我就是世界上 最倒霉的人了
This morning's reading is taken from Matthew, chapter 18, verses 10-14.
今早朗读圣经第18章10一14短诗
"Never despise one of these little ones, I tell you. "
“我对你说 千万不要轻视小事情”
"They have their guardian angels in heaven
“天空中有他们的看守天使
who look continually on the face of my heavenly father. "
坚持不懈的看守著我的神父”
"Suppose a man has a hundred sheep. If one of them strays,
“有个人有100头羊 如果有一头迷路了
does he not leave the other 99 on the hillside
他让其他99头在山坡上
and go in search of the one that strayed?"
而去寻找那头迷路的羊吗？”
"And if he should find it, I tell you this,
“如果他能找到的话 我告诉你
he is more delighted over that sheep than over the 99 that never strayed. "
他对失而复得的那头羊的兴奋 胜过其他99头从未迷路的羊”
"In the same way, it is not your heavenly father's will
“同样的道理 你神父的愿望
that one of these little ones should be lost. " Here ends this morning's reading.
不是那些小事的失去” 今早的朗读到此结束
Stop! Stop that infernal coughing.
不要咳嗽
Every morning alike. Clear your throats on the way to school, not here.
每天来上学的时候路上咳嗽好 不要到这里来
Sounds more like a dirt track than an assembly hall.
声音难听死了
Come out! Come out, that boy!
出来！出来 那个男同学！
Who coughed? Mr Hesketh, somewhere near you, I think.
谁咳嗽的？赫斯凯特先生 我想就在你附近
Fetch that boy out!
把那男孩给我找出来！
MacDowall, it was you. You were coughing.
麦克多沃尔 是你 刚才是你在咳嗽
- It weren't. - Yes, it was. I heard you.
不是 是 我听见你咳嗽了
- It weren't, sir. - Don't argue.
不是的 老师 别争了
- It weren't me, honest. - Headmaster's study.
不是我 真的 校长会调查的
MacDowall! I might have known! Get to my office!
麦克多沃尔！我早就应该知道！ 带到我办公室去！
- It weren't me, sir. - And heaven help you.
不是我 老师 上天会帮助你的
We will now say the Lord's Prayer.
我们现在来祈祷
Hands together, eyes closed.
双手合拢 闭上眼睛
Our Father...
我们的神父…
- Does he bite yer? - He's had a little kid's hand off nearly.
他会咬你吗？ 他还咬了一个小孩子呢
Has it? My, my, my! What's it fastened on? A wire?
是吗？天！上面扣的是什么？电线吗？
Aye. It's broke this off an' all. Just darted at t'kid and got him.
是的 全部弄开了 目标冲著那个孩子并且抓到他了
Well, I don't know, I'm sure. Is that what you've got t'glove on for?
我不知道 但我敢肯定 这就是你带手套的原因
- Yeah. Just in case it gets me. - Aye. Aye.
是的 以防他咬我 是 是的
- What d'yer call it? - Kes.
你叫它什么？凯斯
Kes? Aye. He is a nice bird.
凯斯？好漂亮的一只鸟
I shouldn't like to handle him.
看来我不该买它
Casper! Casper! Up, lad! On yer feet!
卡士柏！站起来！
- You were asleep, weren't you, Casper? - I don't know, sir.
你刚才睡着了 是吗？ 我不知道 老师
I know! You were. You were asleep.
我知道 你刚才睡著了
Why were you asleep, you irreverent scoundrel?
你干吗睡觉？ 你这个目无尊长的东西
- Don't know, sir. - I know why!
不知道 老师 我知道！
You were roaming the streets at night instead of being home in bed.
你晚上在大街上闲逛而不睡觉
See me in my office afterwards! I'll give you something to sleep about! Sit!
下课后到我办公室来！ 我给点东西让你好好睡！坐下！
Here are the announcements.
现在宣告一件事
The youth employment officer will be here today to meet the Easter leavers.
今天将会来一位年轻的教官
Your parents should have been told.
请通知你们父母
If any boy has forgotten and thinks his parents may wish to attend his interview,
如果有人忘了并且认为 他的父母希望参加的话
then he can consult the list on the main notice board for the approximate times.
那他可以把名单写在公告牌上
And finally, for three members of the smokers' union
最后 抽烟团的三个成员
caught yesterday behind the games storeroom,
昨天在操场后面被抓
there will be a meeting with me after assembly,
散会后前来见我
when I will be pleased to see and hear them pay their dues.
我希望听到他们 真诚祈祷他们的罪行
He'd better not stick me. I'm fetchin' me father up if he does.
他最好别指我 否则我不叫我父亲来
What yer bringin' yer father down for? He don't do nowt.
你叫你父亲来干什么？ 他不会做坏事
- How d'yer mean? - Last time, he got stick an' all.
你什么意思？ 上次他就害了我一次
Shut up, will tha? I'm sick of hearin' yer.
你给我闭嘴 好吗？ 我不想听到你说话
When he came, they were laughin' at him.
上次他来的时候 大家都嘲笑他
- Yer what? - Yeah. Weren't they?
你说什么？ 难道不是吗？
Don't say that about my father, right?
别那样说我老爸 知道吗？
He's not gonna beat me, anyhow.
不管怎么样 他不会打我的
- What do you want? - I've got a message for Mr Gryce.
你想干什么？ 格莱斯老师叫我捎信过来
Better wait in the queue, then.
最好排队等候
He likes to keep yer waitin'. He thinks it makes it worse.
他好像要你等 他想这会更糟
He can keep me till four o'clock. I'm not bothered.
他可以叫我等到4点 我不怕麻烦的
I'd rather the cane than do lessons.
我宁愿挨鞭子也不愿去上课
Come here, you.
你过来
Save us these till after we come outta Gryce's.
把我保管好这个 知道我们 从格莱斯老师那出来
He'll think I'm a smoker.
他会认为我会抽烟
He'll not search you but he'll search us, and if he finds 'em, we'll get two extra.
他不会搜你身会搜我们 如果他找到了 我们还另外有两根
- I don't want 'em. - You want some fist instead?
我不保管 你想挨打吗？
- You want to take them? - You'd better, lad.
你愿意保管吗？ 你最好给我放乖点 小子
OK. But if I get caned, you give me something.
好吧 要是我挨鞭的话 你们要给我一些
Aye. Some fist if yer don't.
好的 如果你不的话就要挨打了
'Ey up, he's here - Gryce Pudding.
他来了
Single file.
排好队
Right. You lost, lad?
你掉队了
- Please, sir, I'm going... - On yer way, form room.
老师 请你远离 快到你自己的位置上去
You lot, inside.
你们给我进来
Same old faces.
老油条
Ten years this school's been opened,
学校已经开办10年了
and ten years have we seen, after every assembly, a line of boys here,
每年送走好多学生
and the same old faces.
同样有很多老油条
- Sir, I've got a message... - Shut up. Don't interrupt. Close the door.
老师 别人叫我捎... 闭嘴 别插嘴 关门
I've taught in this city for over 30 years.
我在这里教了30多年书了
I taught some of your parents - your father, MacDowall -
你们当中有些人的父母 还是我的学生呢
in the old slum schools in the city,
麦克多沃尔 你父亲就是
before they built this fine estate, and this wonderful school.
那是在本市的老贫民学校
Things are no better now than they were then.
那时还没有建好这所漂亮的学校
I just can't understand this generation.
现在的情况还不如以前的好
I thought I knew something about young people.
我就是不明白你们这一代人
I should be able to, you know, with my experience.
我自以为多少了解一些你们年轻人 凭我的经验也应该了解
But with you, no.
可是你们就让我看不懂
It just seems a complete waste of money and a waste of time.
这完全是浪费金钱和时间
And it's a waste of time talking to you now.
浪费时间跟你们说这些
- You're not listening, are you? - Yes, sir.
你们不在听我说吗？ 在，老师
You're not! Crossland, you're not listening, are you?
没有！克劳斯兰德 你没有听 是吧？
- I am, sir. - None of you are listening!
老师 我在听 你们谁也不在听！
Look at that glazed expression on your faces.
看看你们脸上的表情
You never listen! Yours is the generation that never listens!
你们根本就不在听！ 你们这一代人根本就不听话！
Cos we can never tell you anything.
因为我们根本教不了你们什么
You're the sophisticated ones,
你们是诡辩的一代人
with all your music, and your gear.
只有你们的音乐和派头
But, you know, it's superficial. It's a sheen.
但这些都是肤浅的 一闪既过的
There's nothing solid or worthwhile underneath.
一文不值
And why do I know this?
我为何知道这个呢？
Why do I know there's been no advance in discipline or decency,
我为何知道 一点好处也没有
or morals or manners?
没有一点道德和礼貌呢？
Why do I know it? Because I still have to use this to you boys every day.
我为何知道？ 因为我每天依然 要用这个来对付你们这些学生
Why? In the '20s and '30s, I could understand it.
为何？在二三十年代 我能理解这个
They were hard times,
那个时候过著艰苦的日子
but they produced qualities in people that you lot will never have.
但是他们毕业的时候有着 你们永远不可能有的教养
I can be stopped in the street by someone I taught then.
我走在大街上有时 会被某个学生叫住
We'll talk about the old days, and we'll laugh about the thrashings I gave him.
谈我们过去的日子 大笑以前我对他们的严厉
But what do I get from you lot?
可我以后和你们谈些什么？
A honk from a greasy, pimply-faced youth
不学无术的年轻人
sitting at the wheel of a big second-hand car.
坐在大的二手车上
I don't know. I just don't know.
我不明白 我就是搞不明白
No guts! No backbone! Nothing to commend you whatsoever.
肚子里一点货也没有！ 根本就是一无是处
Mere fodder for the mass media.
只是一堆草包
And so, until someone produces a better solution,
所以 直到有人提出更好的方法
I'll continue to use this cane,
否则我将一直用这根鞭子
knowing fully well that you'll be back for it time and time and time again.
好好记住你们将随时被挨打
You smokers will go out of here with your hands ringing.
你们几个烟囱出去的时候手被打肿
Will it stop you smoking? You're already looking forward to smoking at break.
这样能阻止你们吸烟吗？ 你们已经指望课后去吸烟
- What are you grinning about? - Not grinnin'.
你们笑什么？没笑
You are! I'll bet you're already thinking about smoking at break.
笑了！你们肯定打算课后去抽烟
Empty your pockets.
翻开你们的口袋
I bet they're loaded with cigarettes. Come on, all of you, empty your pockets.
你们身上肯定还藏有烟 快给我翻过来
- Please, sir... - Quiet. Empty your pockets.
老师…闭嘴 快把你的口袋翻过来
- You don't understand. - Empty your pockets.
你不明白 翻开你们的口袋
Disgusting!
恶心！
Please, sir.
老师 拜托
You again? You again?!
你还说？你还说？！
- Yes, sir. - Empty your pockets.
是 老师 翻开你的口袋
- But, sir, I've got a message from Mrs... - Empty your pockets!
可是 老师 有人叫我给你捎信… 翻开你的口袋！
I don't believe it.
我就是不信
I don't believe this.
我不信这个邪
Empty your pockets, lad. Empty your pockets when you're told!
翻开你的口袋 小子 我叫你翻就得翻！
Come on, lad.
快点 小子
Ah!
你是卷烟厂 是吗？
A regular little cigarette factory, aren't you?
是 老师
Yes, sir.
把垃圾扔掉！
Put that rubbish away!
我希望这对你来说是个教训
Now I hope it's going to be a lesson to you.
我不希望这对你们来说 只有一分钟的教育意义
I don't suppose for one minute it will be.
我敢肯定这个星期结束前 你们还会再回到这里来的
I don't doubt before the end of the week you'll be back in here again
原因一样 那就是抽烟
for exactly the same crime, smoking.
可能你们能躲过一时
Perhaps, once in a while, it might sink in.
但最终我还是会知道的
- Yes, sir. - That you're wasting your money,
是的 老师 你们是在浪费钱
that it's your money you're burning,
你们烧掉的是钱
and it's your hands that get caned when you come in here.
你们进来的时候是你们的手被鞭子打
Good morning. Entry of the gladiators. Where have you been?
早 言归正传 你们到哪去了？
- Been to see Mr Gryce, sir. - For the stick?
老师 我们去了格莱斯 老师那 挨鞭子吗？
- Yes, sir. - How many?
是 老师 打了几下？
- Two. - Did it hurt?
两下 痛吗？
- Not bad. - Right. Hope it didn't.
不是很痛 对 希望没痛
Go on, sit down.
回你们的座位上去吧
Right now, fact.
我们现在来说事实
Anne, tell me what a fact is.
安妮 告诉我事实是什么
Don't give me a fact.
别告诉我事实是…
You know, don't say that Guthrie's got a tatty head or anything like that.
别说嘉塞有个不值钱的头之类的话
A fact is something where you find evidence out, like truth.
事实是一些有证据的东西 像真相一样
Something that you know has actually happened.
一些你的确知道发生了的事情
This is a fact. All right? Have you got that clear?
这就是事实 是吗？你们明白了吗？
- Yes, sir. - All right.
明白 老师 好
Tibbut, sit up straight.
迪柏特 站起来
And I want the rest of yer to look at him - if you can bear it -
其他人看着他...如果你敢保证…
and tell me some facts about Tibbut.
说出一些有关迪柏特的事实
- Wolstenholme? - He's always tryin' to go wi't'lasses.
沃斯特赫姆？他老想进女卫生间
Is he?
是吗？
- He smokes. - Do I heck!
他抽烟 我有吗！
- Tha does. - Get knotted, Guthrie!
你有 别多管闲事 嘉塞！
I'm not interested in what he does out of school hours,
我对他课后干些什么不感兴趣
as long as he doesn't come into the class smokin' a fag. All right?
只要他不在教室里抽烟就行了 对吗？
Come on, you people who aren't thinking.
你们几个快点想啊
Right, Julie.
对 茱莉
I want you to think of an incident that's happened to you sometime in the past,
你自己想想以前你所发生的意外
that is true, and that you think will interest the rest of the class. All right?
要说事实 并且班上其他同 学会感兴趣 好吗？
Well, er...
嗯...
I went to this all-night party yesterday. And, er...
我昨晚参加了通宵派对…
about three o'clock, we were dancin' int' garden -
三点钟左右 我们在花园里跳舞
me and her and all the rest, can't mention names -
我和她以及其他说不出名字的人
and, er, this woman come across from t'road,
有个女人从对面走过来
and, er, she tells us to...
她告诉我们…
to make less noise, or she'd fetch t'police.
别这么大声 否则她就要报警了
So, well... so we said, let her fetch 'em if she wanted.
我们就说 要是她乐意的话 就随她去报警吧
So she fetched 'em.
于是她就报警了
Things that have actually happened. How about another one?
事情的的确确发生了 谁再来说说
What about you, Casper?
你怎么样 卡士柏？
- Casper! - What, sir?
卡士柏！什么事 老师？
"What, sir?" You'd know if you'd been listening.
“什么事 老师” 要是你在听的话
What have we just been talking about?
我们刚才讲什么？
- Stories, sir? - What kind of stories?
讲故事 什么故事？
- You haven't been listening, have yer? - Yes. Some of it.
你刚才根本就不在听 是吗？是的 听了一点点
Some of it?!
一点点？！
Stand up!
站起来！
You're gonna tell us a story about yourself.
和大家说一个有关你自己的故事
- I don't know any, sir. - Well, you stand there till yer do.
我不知道说什么 老师 那好 你站在那 直到会说为止
Always somebody, isn't there, eh? Somebody who wants to be awkward.
总是有这样的人 是吗？ 有人想不好对付他
Just won't be interested, doesn't matter what you do.
只是没有兴趣 你所做的一点关系也没有
Just like you, Casper.
正如你一样 卡士柏
Come on.
说吧
I'll give you two minutes
我给你两分钟时间考虑
to think of something, or the whole class comes back at four o'clock.
否则全班同学4点钟回来
- Come on, don't stand there like a nail. - He is a nail.
快想啊 别像根钉子一样站在那 他就是根钉子
Come on.
快点
- I say... tell him. - Tell him about the hawk, Casper.
照我看…告诉他 卡士柏 说说有关鹰的事
If anybody else calls out, it'll be the last call they make!
要是谁再出声的话 这可是最后一次机会了！
- Speed? - He's got this hawk. He's mad over it.
斯皮德？他捡到一 只鹰 收养起来了
He just goes wi't'hawk all t'time. He's crackers over it.
把鹰一直带在身边
- Better than thee, anyroad. - All right, Casper.
你别乱说话 好了 卡士柏
Sit down.
坐下
Now, come on, tell us about this hawk. Where'd you get it from?
给大家说说那只鹰 你是从哪儿捡到的？
- I found it, sir. - Where?
我看到的 老师 在哪？
- Int' woods. - Where d'you keep it?
在树林里 你把鹰放在哪？
- In a shed. - What do you feed it on?
笼子 你用什么喂它？
Beef. Mice. Birds.
牛肉 老鼠还有小鸟
Isn't it cruel to keep it in a shed? Wouldn't it be happier flying free?
放在笼子对它不是很残酷吗？ 让其自由飞翔不是更好吗？
I don't keep it int' shed all the time, sir. I fly it every day.
我不是每天把它关在笼子里 每天都会放飞它
- Doesn't it fly away? - Course it don't fly away. I've trained it.
它不会飞走吗？当然不会了 我训练它了
Are you gonna tell us about it? How do you train a hawk?
你对我们说说你是 怎么训练鹰的 好吗？
You have to be right careful wi' 'em, sir, right patient.
就是要有耐心 仔细的喂养它们
You've got to feed 'em when they're hungry.
他们饿的时候必须给他们食物
You can only do owt at feedin' time, sir.
在喂养的时候什么事也做不了
- Yeah? - Got these jesses on, sir, all t'time.
是吗？还要系上鹰的脚带
- These what? - Jesses, sir.
什么啊？鹰的脚带
- How do you spell that? - J-e...
怎么拼写？J一E…
All right. Come out here. You'd better show us on the board.
好了 你最好到黑板上写出来
"Jesses". That's a new word to me.
“鹰的脚带“ 对我来说可是个新单词
Hands up those who've heard of jesses before?
以前听说过鹰的脚带的请举手
Nobody. Go on, write it up there.
没人 来 写出来
Right. Now tell us what it is.
好了 告诉我们是什么东西
They're leather straps, sir. And they attach to t'bird's feet.
是皮革带子 用来系鸟类的脚的
Say I've got t'bird on me hand. Straps come down there. Then there's t'swivel.
比方说我手上有只鸟 带子从这下面穿过来 再转个身
"Swivel". Write that on the board.
“转身“ 写到黑板上
- Then you've got your leash. - "Leash". On the board.
这样就栓著了把“栓“写在黑板上
I fed it on me hand first.
我先在手上给它喂食
Then, when it got to know me, I fed it on me glove.
当它开始认得我的时候 就在手套上给他喂食
And after a while, I put it two inches away from its claws.
一段时间过后 我把它放在离其爪子两英寸的地方
And, er... Like that, right?
就这样
It started to jump for t'meat. When it started to jump, I could move me hand.
他就跳起来吃东西 它跳起来的时候 我就可以移开我的手
- Hold your hand up, so we can see. - I could move me hand away, like,
把头拾起 我们可以看到 我可以这样把我的手拿开
to four inches and six inches. And when it were doin' that, I started it wi't'leash.
到了4至6英寸的时候 鹰就 这样了 我就可以开始拴了
Do they need water? When you've got a budgie, you put water in the cage.
需要水吗？饲养相思鹦鹉的 时候 把水放在笼子里
Do they need water like that?
鹰也是那样进水吗？
Well, it, like, has a bath. It has a bath right early on int' morning, like.
就拿洗澡来说吧 鹰在一大早就洗澡
When do yer feed it? How many times a day?
你什么时候喂它？一天喂几次？
To start off with, three or four, to get it plump.
大约三四次吧
- You make it sound very exciting. - It is.
听起了好像很过瘾 是的
Most exciting thing was when I flew her free first time.
更过瘾的是我第一次放飞它
- Do you wanna hear about that? - Yes, sir.
大家想听听吗？想 老师
Aye. Come on.
你说来听听
Well, I'd been using t'creance for about a week,
我用了折缝大约一个星期的时候
and it had been goin' 30 or 40 yards.
走了三四十码的时候
And it says when birds are goin' 30-40 yards, it says int' book,
书上说当鸟走了三四十码的时候
it's time that it can start to fly free.
它就可以开始飞了
Well, I'd been...
我...
I'd been wantin' to fly it free, but I daren't. I were frightened it'd fly off or somethin'.
我一直在等他能飞 可我 不敢 我很怕他会飞走
This had been goin' on for four or five days.
这样矛盾了三四天
And I keep on to missen, sayin' that "Fly it free next day. "
心里总对自己说“明天就让它飞“
Anyway, I got right mad wi' missen. I says "Right, I'm flyin' it free tomorrow. "
可我心里还是担心它会飞走 我说“好 就明天放飞它吧”
Anyway, that night - that Friday night it were -
那个晚上 星期五那个晚上…
I didn't feed her up, so that she'd be sharp set next mornin'.
我没有喂他 那样它第二天早上飞得更快
And I went to bed that night, Friday night, and I didn't get an hour's sleep at all.
那晚我睡到床上 可一刻也睡不着
I were frightened about t'bird, that she'd fly off or summat like that.
我担心它飞走再也不回来了
Anyway, when t'mornin' came, I kept on sayin' to missen
第二天早上来临 我总对自己说
"If she flies off, she flies off, and it can't be helped. "
“如果它会飞走的话 就让他飞走吧 那是没办法的事情”
So I took t'swivel off and let her hop onto t'post.
于是我解开栓子让它飞到杠子上去
There were nowt stoppin' her, she could fly off. All that were on her were jesses.
没有什么牵制它了 它可以飞走了
I thought "She must fly off. She's forced to fly off. "
我心里想“它肯定会飞走 一定会飞走”
But she didn't. She just stood there. I were terrified.
可是它没有 一动不动的站在那儿 我怕了
She was stood there, and I walked off into t'field, and she were lookin' round,
它总站在那儿 我走到田野里 它就四周看看
and when I got about 70 yards from her, in middle of t'field,
当我远离它70码的地方 在田野中间
I called her.
我叫它
"Kes. Kes. Come on, Kes. Come on, then. "
“凯斯 凯斯 过来 过来”
Nowt happened. So I thought "I'd better walk back and pick her up. "
它没有过来 所以我就想 “我还是回去捡回它来”
So while I were walkin' back, I saw her flyin'. She came like a bomb!
当我回去的时候 我看到它忽然间飞起来！
About a yard off t'floor, like lightning, head still, and you couldn't hear t'wings.
在离地面一码的地方保持不动 在那里飞翔
There weren't a sound from t'wings. And straight onto t'glove. Wham!
翅膀一点声音也没有 直接飞到手套上来
And she grabbed me for t'meat.
它抓着我要肉吃
I were pleased wi' missen, and I didn't know what to do.
我很高兴它会回来 我不知道该怎么办
So I thought I better do it again, just to prove it weren't luck.
于是我想要再来一次 证明这不是运气
So I took her back onto t'post,
于是我把它带回那杠子上
and walked up into t'middle of t'field, and called her again.
我走到田野中间再次叫它
And she came just as good as first time, straight onto t'glove, grabbin' for t'meat.
它像第一次一样飞得那么好 径直飞到手套上 抓着要肉吃
Well, that were it, sir. I'd trained her, sir, and that were all I could do.
就这样 老师 我训练了它 我也只能这样做
I think you've done enough. Well done, Billy. Big hand of applause.
我想你做的很好 很好 比利 大家掌声鼓励一下
- Got owt, Casper? - Nay.
没什么事吗 卡士柏？没有
Tha never has. Tha just cadges. Casper the Cadger, they ought to call thee.
你向来都是这样 他们叫你二流子
- I wouldn't give thee owt if I had. - I'll give thee summat.
我就是有的话也不会给你的 我会给你算数求和
What tha goin' for? Don't tha like company?
你去干吗？ 你不喜欢和大家玩吗？
They say thi mother does. Tha's got more uncles than any other kid.
他们说你妈也是这样 你比其他孩子更多舅舅
- Shut thi mouth! - Make me.
你给我闭嘴！来打我啊
- Tha wouldn't say that to our Jud. - Your Jud's nowt.
别这样对我们的祖德说话 你们的祖德是坏人
What? He's cock of t'estate.
什么？他是那个时期的老大
- I know somebody who could do him. - Who? Thi father?
我知道有人有办法对付他 谁？你父亲？
- He in't even thi brother. - What is he? Me sister?
他又不是你兄弟 那他是什么？我姐姐吗？
They don't even call him Casper.
他们不是叫他卡士柏
Course he's me brother! We live int' same house, don't we?
他当然是我大哥！ 我们住在同一个屋檐下
Get him! Get him!
打他！打他！
Fight!
打！
Right, you lot! Ten seconds, out of my sight!
你们十秒钟给我消失！
One! Two! Three!
1  2  3 !
Right, come here, you two. Come on.
你们两个给我过来
- What's goin' on? - It was him, sir. He started it.
怎么回事？老师 是他先动手打人的
- He's been chuckin' coal. - Ah, shut up. Shut up!
他在扔煤 闭嘴！闭嘴！
It's always the same tale; somebody else's fault, nobody's to blame.
总是同一个故事：谁都有错 到头来谁都不用挨骂
Look at the mess you're in! Look at the state you've made!
瞧瞧你们多
- Casper, you're not dead yet. - He will be when I've had him.
卡士柏 你还活着 等我收拾他
Oh, yes! You're a big lad, aren't yer? He's just about your size, Casper, isn't he? Eh?
是啊！你个子大条多了 你跟卡士柏个子差不多 是吗？
Pick on somebody your own size.
去找大条点的单挑去
What if I rubbed your nose in the coke? You'd say I was a bully, wouldn't yer?
要是我欺负你 你会不会说我无耻？
And you'd be right. Cos I'm bigger and stronger than you, aren't I? Eh?
对 我是无耻 因为我个子比你大条
- I'll fetch me dad. - Oh, yes. And I'll fetch mine.
那我就告诉我爸爸 行啊，我也叫我爸爸来跟你爸爸单挑
My dad's heavyweight champion of the world,
我爸爸是世界重量级冠军
so what will your dad do then, eh?
你爸会怎么办？
That's what it's like to be bullied. You don't like it, do yer?
欺凌弱小 你也不喜欢的 对吗？
You'll like it a bit less if I ever catch you at it again. Do you understand it?
再让我见到你的话 你就有好戏看 明白吗？
Yes, sir.
知道了
Get it shovelled up. Come here a minute. Have you been smoking?
快把这些铲好 过来一下 你抽烟了？
- No, sir. - You have! I can smell it on your breath.
没有 你抽烟了！全是烟味
- See me afterwards. Get it done. Go on.
没有 马上收拾干净 等下我来不想再见到这些东西 快
What's it all about?
到底怎么回事？
He keeps callin' me names, and sayin' things about me dad and me mam and...
他不停叫我的外号 还说我爸妈
All right, all right, all right. Calm down.
好了…别说了
They all seem to pick on you. Why is it?
看来他们看你不顺眼 怎么会这样？
- Don't know. - Is it because you're a bad 'un?
不知道 就因为你是个捣蛋鬼？
Maybe I am sometimes, but I'm not that bad, sir.
也许有时候捣蛋 但我还没那么坏
I know stacks of other kids that's worse than me, but they seem to get away wi' it.
我认识许多比我还坏的孩子 但他们还没那么被人瞧不起
Why else do you think, eh? There must be some reason.
干嘛这么认为？ 一定还有别的原因
Well, take this mornin', sir.
那是今天早上的事
I came in and just dozed off. I weren't doin' nowt wrong.
我只是打磕睡而已 我没做错什么事情
I'd been up since six. I had to do t'papers, then I had to rush home to look at t'bird,
我今天六点就起床了 我得去 送报纸 然后急急忙忙回家喂鸟
and then run to school. You'd be tired, wouldn't yer, sir?
接着上学 是你的话 你也会累的 对吗？
I'd be exhausted.
何止累呢 我会筋疲力尽的
You shouldn't be caned for that, sir. And you can't tell Mr Gryce that.
你不该打我 也不该告诉格莱斯先生
And this little lad, sir. He'd only brought a letter from a teacher, and he got t'cane.
不能就因为收到老师的状告就挨打
It's nowt to laugh at, sir. Afterwards, he was sick as a dog.
没什么好笑的 接著他就病倒了
And teachers, sir. They're not bothered about us, sir.
还有老师们 他们对我们漠不关心
If we're 4C, they think we're numbskulls, owt like that, sir.
如果我们成绩不好 他们就把我们当作傻瓜
They're always lookin' at their watches, to see how long there's left of t'lesson.
他们总是看手表 希望快点下课
They're not bothered about us, and we're not bothered about them.
他们根本不在乎我们 我们也不在乎他们
How are things at home these days?
家里最近怎样？
All right, sir. Usual, I suppose.
估计还行 老样子
- Been in trouble with the police recently? - No, sir.
最近有没有找警察的麻烦？没有
Not since I've been without MacDowall's gang.
自从我不跟麦克多沃尔 那帮人玩以后就学好了
You know, they used to go into t'city and go into t'coffee bars and t'cinema,
他们经常进城泡吧看电影
but since I've been without them I've been all right.
自从我洗手不干以后 我就没干坏事了
- It's all right now, innit? - But when there's trouble on estate,
确实没干坏事了？ 不过有什么案件的时候
all the police come to our house.
警察就来我们家
Well, I shouldn't worry.
那好 我这就放心多了
In a couple of weeks you'll be starting your new job, gettin' new friends.
几个星期内 你就能找份新的工作 结识新的朋友了
Lookin' forward to that, are yer? Eh? Have you got a job?
你也希望这样吧？ 你找到工作了吗？
No, sir. I've got to see t'employment bloke.
还没有 我得去见工
- What sort of job do you want? - Anything'll do me.
你想找什么工作？ 无所谓
But you want something that you're interested in, don't you?
起码是你干兴趣的才行吧？
- I'll take what I've got. - I thought you wanted to leave school.
我要我应得的就行了 我倒认为你想离开学校
- Not bothered. - Thought you didn't like school.
别担心 因为你不喜欢上学
I don't, but it dun't mean to say I'll like work. Still, I'll get paid for not likin' it.
我不喜欢上学并不等于我喜欢工作 何况我已经付出代价了
- That's one thing. - I suppose it is.
就是这样 我想也是
I might be able to save up and buy a goshawk. I've been readin' about 'em.
我想攒钱买只鹰 我看好了
Have yer? When do you fly this hawk o' yours?
是吗？ 你什么时候驯鹰？
- Dinner times. - Where?
吃晚饭的时候 在哪？
- Just outside our house, sir. - Wood Lane?
就在我家附近 在树林那边的路上？
- Yeah, it is, sir. - I'll come round, then. If it's OK.
对 有时间我会去看看的
Go on, then. Get yourself cleaned up.
去吧 把脸洗干净
"Five bob double. Crackpot. Tell Him He's Dead. "
五先令买双倍卡拉克帕特 告诉他他死了
"Jud. "
祖德
Bloody hellfire!
真他妈的操蛋！
Kes! Come on, then.
凯斯！来
Kes!
凯斯！
Come on, then, Kes.
快来 凯斯
Come on.
快抓住 凯斯
Casper?
卡士柏
Bloody hellfire!
见鬼！
- Hope I'm not too late. - No. But you'll have to stand over there.
希望我没来迟 没有 不过你别过来
- I'll go by the fence, eh? - It's all right.
我站在围墙那行吗？ 站那边就行了 不要紧
- As long as you keep quiet. - I'll not say a word.
别说话就行了 好的
Come on, Kes!
来啊 凯斯
Kes!
凯斯！
Well done, Casper. The most exciting thing I've ever seen in me life. Great!
漂亮 卡士柏 真是让我大开眼界 太棒了！
- Thrill of a lifetime, lad. - Thank you, sir.
真刺激 过奖了
Let's have a look at it.
给我看看
Isn't it beautifully marked, eh?
真漂亮
Look at the feathers on it. Oh, it's not gonna eat that, is it?
羽毛真好看 它吃这个？
Yes, sir. This bird's full of vitamins.
对 鸟肉富含维他命
Oh, dear!
天啊！
- Have any more birds before him? - Stacks. Animals an' all.
以前养过别的动物吗？ 多了 全都是野生的
A young fox cub once. Reared it and let it go. A little blinder!
还养过狐狸 养大后放生了 很可爱的！
I've had magpies, jackdaws. Had a young jay once.
还有喜鹊和乌鸦 还有一只小松鸦
- He's your favourite, though. - Others weren't int' same street.
它是你的最爱 这大街上找不到第二只这样的鸟
Come on, then. Come on.
来
- Come on, sir. - Oh, dear me!
跟我来 噢 真绝了！
- Watch that mattress, sir. It's slippy. - OK.
当心这个垫子 很滑的
Look what's left, sir.
看看剩下什么了
Only t'sparrow's leg. Must have been hungry.
只剩下鸟腿了一定是饿坏了
Must have been starvin'.
简直要饿死了
You hang on here. I'll put him ont' perch.
你站在这 我进去放好它
Come on, then.
来
You know, there's something weird about it when it's flyin'.
它飞起来的时候有一种神秘的力量
- Hawks are t'best fliers there is. - No, I didn't mean that.
鹰是最棒的飞行家 我不是指这个
When it's flyin', there's something about it makes you feel strange.
它飞着的时候 有一种怪异的感觉
- Is it cos everythin' goes quiet? - That's it, aye.
是因为安静的缘故吗？是的
Other folks have noticed that. I know a farmer who says it's same wi' owls.
其他人也感觉到了 有个农夫说它跟猫头鹰一样
You know, when they get his mice in his yard at night.
晚上他们吃老鼠的时候
When they swoop down, he feels like pokin' his ears to make 'em pop.
当他们扑食的时候 他觉得自己好害怕
Cos it goes that quiet.
因为他们是悄无声息的致命天敌
It's as if they're flying in a pocket of silence.
就像是在幽静的口袋里飞翔一样
Have you noticed how quietly we're speaking?
你没意识到我们说话的声音很小吗？
As if we're frightened to raise our voices, a bit like shouting in church.
好像我们不敢大声说话一样
- It's cos they're nervous. - Oh, no. It's more than that.
是因为他们感到不安 不 不只是不安
It's instinctive. It's a sort of respect.
是一种本能一种尊严
I know, sir. That's what makes me mad. When I take her for walks, somebody says
我知道 这就是让我着迷的原因 我带鸟出去的时候 有人说
"Look, it's Billy Casper and his pet hawk. "
快看啊 是比利 卡士柏和他的宠物鹰
I could shout at 'em, sir. It in't a pet.
我就大声喊：它不是宠物
Or if somebody comes up to me and says "Is it tame?"
或者如果有人说：这鸟是不是驯过的？
Is it heck tame! Hawks can't be tamed.
驯过的！鹰是不能驯服的
They're manned. It's wild and it's fierce and it's not bothered about anybody.
他们只不过是被人操纵而已 他们本性暴庚狂野 不怕任何人
Not bothered about me, right. That's what makes it great.
不怕我 这就是伟大的地方
A lot of people wouldn't understand. They like their pets to be fussed.
很多人不会了解的 他们喜欢宠物受宠若惊的样子
I'm not bothered about that. I just want her for her looks and to fly her.
我才不管这个 我只是想看放飞他们的风采
They can keep their talkin' budgies. They're nowt compared wi' her.
他们可以教鹦鹉说话 但是鹦鹉跟它是不能比的
You're right, Billy. You're probably right.
你说得对 比利
D'you know summat, sir? I think she's done me a favour, lettin' me watch her.
知道吗？我觉得它帮了我个大忙 让我照顾它
"Same price, 7-1, number 12, Doorkeeper. "
一样的价钱 7一1 12号 看门人
What's he studyin' there?
他来这学什么？
- Can I help you, son? - No, thanks.
要帮忙吗 孩子？不用了 谢谢
Hey, mister, can you tell me t'prices of these?
先生 能告诉我价钱吗？
What are they?
什么价钱？
Crackpot.
卡拉克帕特
Crackpot. 100-6.
卡拉克帕特100一6
Tell Him He's Dead. I've just been lookin' for this one meself.
告诉他他死了 我自己就一直在找这个
Second favourite, 4-1.
告诉他他死了第二买4一1
100-6, 4-1.
100一6  4一1
Would you back 'em?
你会跟吗？
Tell Him He's Dead's a good horse. Best horse int' race. Top weight.
告诉他他死了 是一匹好马 最好的马是不会比赛的
Don't fancy that one, though.
但别指望太高
No form. Hasn't even got a jockey on here. No, shouldn't bother with that one.
没有表格是找不到好马的
D'yer think they'll win, then?
他们会赢吗？
- How've you got them? Doubled? - They're our Jud's.
你是怎么找到的？ 买双倍了吗？是祖德
Oh, he'll be all right if they do, but I can't see it meself.
如果能赢 他就神了 我不认为他能赢
Right. Ta.
对 再见
- A bob's worth o' chips, and a fish. - Serve him, will you, Mary?
芝士饼和一条鱼 玛丽 给他准备
- Yes, love? What do you want? - Fish 'n' chips.
你想买什么？鱼和芝士饼
Stop kickin'. We only put that on today.
别敲了 我们今天刚换的
- Got any scraps, missis? - Yes, love. I'll put you some on.
有面包屑吗？有 给你一点
Two shilling, love. I'm gettin' rid of these chips, Floyd. It's gettin' late now.
一共2先令 我正想丢掉这些芝士饼 弗洛伊德 已经不新鲜了
Aye. But don't be goin' mad.
行了 别发疯
Sixpence change, love.
找你6便士
These kids. I don't know, Mr Glover, they're just all the same.
我搞不懂这些孩子？格罗夫先生 他们就是这个样子了
- Can I have a quarter o' beef? - By, those smell good.
给我来点牛肉 真香
Can I have a quarter o' beef?
给我点牛肉 行吗？
- Tha still got that bird, then? - Yep.
你还养那条鸟吗？是的
- Here, you can have them for nowt. - For nowt?
喂狗还好点 喂狗？
- They're only scraps. - Another chip?
对啊 还吃吗？
- No. I'm goin' for me dinner in a minute. - Right, then. See yer.
不吃了 我等下就吃晚饭了 那好 回头见
See yer.
回头见
Usual difficulty over concentration. Hm?
集中听讲还是很难 是吗？
Three fives are 15, eh?
三五得五
We write 15 one, five. You write five, one.
15个1加起来就是15
Oi, tha fuckin' twat!
该死的兔患子！
Isn't that that illustrious brother of yours, Casper?
卡士柏 是你的哥哥吗？
Shouldn't have thought he was the type to have paid a visit to his old school again.
他该不会是怀念母校了吧？
- What's the matter? Don't you feel well? - No, sir.
- 怎么回事？你不觉得舒服吗？ - 没有 老师
- Do you want to go for a drink of water?
要喝水吗？不要
- Well, open the window. - I'm all right, sir.
要不要开窗？我没事 老师
Please yourself.
随你便
Right, now just pass your books forward, will you? To the front.
把作业本传到前面来吧
Front person on each row, bring them to my desk, will you?
第一排的同学把作业收给我 好吗？
What's the matter, Casper? Lost something?
有事吗 卡士柏？东西不见了吗？
- Me, sir? No, sir. - On your way, then.
我？我没丢东西 那就走吧
- What's up with thee, Jud? - It's that little bastard, our Billy.
你怎么了 祖德？ 是哪个兔崽子 比利
I left him with a bet for t'horses and he's kept t'stinkin' money. I'll kill the little git!
我让他拿钱去赛马 他却把钱私藏起来 我要杀了他
- What are you playing at? - Goin' to t'toilet, sir.
你在干什么？上洗手间 老师
Hurry up, then.
那快点
- I'm on 'ere! - Seen our Billy?
是我在这！看见了比利吗？
- Aye. He's here wi' me. - Tryin' to be funny?
他同我在这 开玩笑吗？
Cos I'll stick thi head down there, old pal, and flush it.
我头都快垫进去了 朋友 帮帮忙吧
- I asked if tha'd seen him. - I wouldn't tell thee if I had.
我问你是否见过他 知道也不会告诉你
- Look, I'm warnin' yer! - Ow!
我警告你！哦！
'Ey up, Tibbut, has tha seen our Jud?
迪柏特 看见了祖德吗？
- They've been lookin' all over for thee. - Who has?
他们到处找你 谁？
- Gryce Pudding. - What for?
格莱斯 为什么？
Youth Employment. Tha should have gone for t'interview.
新的工作 你应该去面试
- Has tha seen our Jud? - Yeah. He wanted to know where tha was.
你看见了祖德吗？看见了 他想知道你在哪里
- Where the devil have you been? - Nowhere, sir.
你到底去哪了？没去哪 老师
Nowhere? Who are you, the Invisible Man?
没去哪？你是谁 隐形人吗？
I felt sick, sir, so I went to t'toilets.
我有点不舒服 我去洗手间了
What happened? Did you drop down it? I've had prefects looking for you!
怎么了？掉进洗手间吗？ 我一直在找你！
- I went out for a breath of fresh air. - Where are you going now?
我出去呼吸了一下新鲜空气 现在要去哪？
- Employment officer. - For your interview? Get off, then, lad!
职业介绍所 因为你的面试？ 那么出发吧！
And God help your future employer!
上帝会帮助你未来的雇主
- Sit up, Peter. - I'm sat up.
坐好 皮特 我坐好了
And don't be like a dummy when you get in there.
当你进来这里时别象哑巴一样
Just tell him you're after a good job, in an office or something like that.
告诉他 你寻找一份工作 在一个办公室那种类型的
I'm not working in no office!
我不会在办公室工作
- What are you after? A job on the bins? - Can't you shut up?
那你寻找什么样的工作？一份储仓库的工作 你可以不要说话吗？
- Sit up. - I'm sat up.
坐好 我坐好了
- And straighten your tie. - Tha's naggin'.
打直你的领带 如此唠叨
Somebody's got to nag.
任何人都会发唠叨
Is it yer mam?
是你妈妈吗？
- What job are tha after? - Owt'll do me.
你寻找什么工作 任何事都可以
- It certainly won't. - It will.
当然不是 是
- It won't. - Right. Thank you.
不是的 对 谢谢
Will you send the next one in?
你会把下一个送进来吗？
- Pardon? - Will you send the next one in, please?
什么？请把下一个送进来？
- Isn't it your turn to go in? - Suppose so.
不是轮到你进来了吗？我想是吧
Well, go on, then.
好了 那么进去吧
Get out! Knock and wait.
出去！敲门等着
Come in.
进来
Well, come in, lad, if you're coming.
好 既然你来了 进来吧
- Sit down, Walker. - I'm not Walker, sir.
坐下 沃克 我不是沃克 先生…
Who are you, then? On my list it should be Gerald Walker next.
那你是谁？我名单上 下一个是杰尔德 沃克
Oliver, Stenton, then Walker.
奥利弗 斯坦顿 然后是沃克
- I'm Casper. - Casper.
我是卡士柏 卡士柏？
Oh, sit down, Casper. I should have seen you earlier, shouldn't I?
哦 坐下 卡士柏 我本应该更早些引见你 不是吗？
Well, then, Casper, what kind of job had you got in mind?
好了 卡士柏 你想找什么样的工作？
Well?
怎么？
I don't know, sir. I haven't thought about it.
我不知道 先生 我没有想过
You should be thinking about it. You want to start off on the right foot, don't you?
你应该想想 你想从 右脚开始 不是吗？
Right, then. Would you like to work in an office?
好了 你想在办公室工作吗？
- Or would you prefer manual work? - What's manual work?
还是你更喜欢手工劳动？ 什么是手工劳动？
It means working with your hands. Things like farming, engineering, plumbing.
那意味着用你的手劳动 比如说 耕作 工程以及铅工业
Things like that, as opposed to penpushing jobs.
就是那样的事 被认为是艰辛的工作
I'd be all right in an office. I have a job to read and write.
我在一个办公室会很好 我有一份工作要阅读和写作
"Manual".
手工
Tell me, Casper, have you ever thought about entering a trade as an apprentice?
告诉我 卡士柏 你曾经想 过进入一项生意做一名学徒吗？
You know, as an electrician or a bricklayer or something like that.
你知道 比如说一名电工 砖匠还是什么的
Of course, the money's not too good while you're serving your apprenticeship,
当然 在你做学徒时拿不到到很多钱
but you'll always have a trade at your fingertips, won't you?
但你总是喜欢用手工作 不是吗？
Well, what do you think about it?
好了 你对此认为怎样？
As you've said, you feel better working with your hands. Perhaps this is the best.
像你说的那样 你用手工作 感觉会更好 或许这是最好的
Of course, you'd have to go to technical college and study for examinations.
当然 你得去技校学习通过考试
Some lads do it. Some do it for years, two or three nights a week,
有些家伙那样做了 有些已经做几年了 一周两三个晚上
right from leaving school right up to mid-twenties,
二十几岁就离开学校
when they take their Higher National, or even degrees.
当他们拿到比较好的成绩时
I say, lad. Are you listening to me?
小子 你在听我说吗？
- Yeah. - You don't look as though you are.
我在听啊 可是你看来好像不在听
I've other lads to see before four o'clock, you know.
四点之前我要看到其他小伙子
If nothing I've mentioned appeals to you,
如果我对你提的要求 对你没事的话
and if you can stand a hard day's work and don't mind getting dirty,
如果你可以努力工作 一天而不弄脏的话
- there are good opportunities in mining. - I'm not goin' down t'pit.
可以给你一个采矿的好机会 我不下矿井
Don't be put off by what you've heard. Conditions have improved tremendously.
别搪塞你所听到的形势 已经变得十分恶劣
I wouldn't be seen dead down t'pit.
我不想看到那矿井
What about hobbies? What hobbies have you got?
有什么业余爱好？
Do you like gardening, or constructing Meccano sets, or anything like that?
你喜欢园艺之类的工作吗？
- Don't you have any hobbies at all? - Can I go now?
你什么爱好也没有吗？ 我可以走了吗？
What's wrong with you, lad? Sit down. Sit down, I haven't finished yet.
小伙子 你怎么啦？ 坐下 坐下 我还没有说完呢
I've met some lads in my time, but I've never met one like you.
我一生中见过很多小伙子 从未见过像你这样的
Half the time you're like a cat on hot bricks, the other half you're not listening.
一半时间你像只老鼠站在 热砖块上 另一半时间你不在听
Here. Take this form.
给你这张表格
It gives you information about leaving school and starting work.
能给你一些离开学校 参加工作的信息
Things like pensions, superannuation, national insurance, wages.
像养老金 退休金 保险金 工资之类的
At the back, there's a detachable form. When you want your cards, fill it in...
背后有张可拆开的表格 当你需要卡片的时候 填上去...
Come back, lad. I haven't finished yet.
回来 小伙子 我还没有说完呢
When you want your cards, fill in that form, send it in. Got that?
当你需要卡片的时候填好表格 交上来 知道吗？
- Yeah. - Don't forget. And listen, Casper.
知道 别忘了 听好 卡士柏
If you do have trouble getting fixed up, come in and see me.
如你遇到什么麻烦 过来找我
- Yeah. - Send the next boy in.
是 叫下一个小伙子进来
Kes!
凯斯！
Jud?
祖德？
Jud?! Mother?!
祖德？妈？！
- Missis, have you seen our Jud? - I haven't, love. Sorry.
太太 你见我家祖德了吗？ 没有 孩子 对不起
- Have you seen our Jud? - Course I've seen him.
您见我家祖德了吗？ 我当然见他了
- Doesn't look as though you've seen him. - You've seen him, then?
好像你没有见到他 你见他了 是吗？
Course I've seen him. Come in here playin' hell. Goin' to pull t'counter down.
我当然见他了 进去推开那柜台
I had to fetch Eric Clough to prove tha hadn't put t'bet on.
我必须叫艾里克来证明他没有赌博
- They won, then, did they? - Both of 'em. 100-6 and 4-1.
那他们赢了 是吗？ 都赢了 100比6和4比1
- He'd have won a tenner, I tell thee that. - Bloody hell.
他赢了10块 糟糕
Kes!
凯斯！
Come on, Kes!
出来啊 凯斯！
Come on, lass!
出来！
Kes!
凯斯！
Come on, Kes!
快出来 凯斯！
- Where is it? What's tha done wi' it? - Where've you been? Your tea's cold.
- 到哪去了？你把我的鹰弄到哪去了？ - 你去哪了？你的茶都凉了
I said, where is it?
我问你我的鹰哪去了？
- What's tha starin' at? - Thee, tha little pig!
我盯著我看什么？你这混蛋！
Don't call me a little pig!
别叫我混蛋！
Hey! Hey!
嘿！嘿！
Jud, what's all t'bloody pushin' and shovin'?
祖德 什么事发这么大火？
- Ask him. He knows. - Tha'd have known if I'd got hold o' thee.
你问他就知道了 要是我打你的话你就知道了
- Oh, get lost! - Knows what?
给我滚蛋 知道什么？
What's goin' off? What's up wi' him?
发生什么事了？他怎么啦？
If he'd have put that bet on, there wouldn't have been none of this.
如果他给我下赌注的话 现在就不会这个样子了
- He's put it on, hasn't he? - Has he bloody hell!
他已经下了 不是吗？他下个屁！
- I told him to. I asked you not to forget. - He didn't forget. He spent t'money!
我叫了他下注的。我还特意提醒他别忘了 他没忘 他把钱给花了！
How d'you know?
你怎么知道？
What you gettin' so upset for? Have they won?
你干吗这么紧张？赢了吗？
Have they won?! I'd have 16 quid if he'd kept his thieving hands to hisself.
赢了吗？！要是他不花了我的钱 我就有16傍了！
- Look what you've done. - Should have done it thissen.
看看你做的好事
- I could have a week off work for that! - Get lost, you big pig!
那钱我要干一个星期才能赚回来！ 滚开 你这头大笨猪！
Hey! Well, what's he upset for?
他紧张什么？
Because he's killed me hawk instead, that's why.
因为他杀了我的鹰
- He never has. - I know he has. Cos he couldn't catch me.
他没有 我知道是他 因为他没有抓到我
- Jud! You have not killed this kid's hawk! - So I have. What yer gonna do about it?
祖德！ 你没有杀你弟弟的鹰！ 我杀了 你又能拿我怎么样？
Killing yerself, that's what you want!
你去死吧！
It were its own fault. I were only gonna let it go.
要怪只能怪那鹰自己 我只想放走它而已
Kept lashin' at me wi't'claws. I had to kill it.
可它总不停的抓 我没办法才杀它
You're a big bastard! A big rotten bastard!
你这混蛋！大王八蛋！
Don't call me a bastard! Tha'll be next to get it!
别叫我王八蛋！否则下一个就是你！
You're a big bastard! A big bleedin' bastard!
你这个大王八蛋！ 特大王八蛋！
- Enough of that language! - I could have had a lousy week off work.
别骂了！本来我可以好好休息一个星期的
- What you done wi't'bird? - It's int' bin!
你对那鹰怎么啦？
You want puttin' int' bin! Look what you've done to him!
看看你做的好事！
- If I'd got hold of him, he'd have been in! - Oh, yes, you!
要是让我抓到它 它肯定 没好日子过！应该是你
- That's just about your bloody... - Shut yer face!
只是你那该死的…给我滚蛋！
You shut your face! Don't talk to me like that or I'll shut it for yer!
别再让我看到你！不然我揍扁你
Ar, no, yer wouldn't dare!
你不敢！
Don't tempt me too much, cos I'm sick of it now!
别刺激我了 我现在都要忍不住了！
- Ah, shut up! - And you! I'm fed up of bein' int' house!
闭嘴！闭嘴的是你不然我赶你出家门！
- I'm fed up of seein' yer in. - Upsettin't'kid like that!
我谅你也不敢把你弟弟弄成那个样子！
Bloody pig, yer are.
你这大混蛋！
Look what he's done, Mam. Look at it. He's a right 'un.
妈妈 看他干的 你看看
- That were a rotten trick! - It were a rotten trick what he did to me!
看你干的好事！ 他干的才是好事呢！
Yer could have took it out o' me!
你可以带出来给我的！
You know what a lot he thought about it. Take it away from t'table.
你知道这小鹰对他来 说有多重要吗！ 拿开
- What yer gonna do to him? - What d'yer want me to do?
你说该怎么对他？你想我怎么做？
- Give him a good hidin'. - What d'you think yer...
好好埋葬他 你想干什么你…
Yes. I'd just like to see her, an' all.
太好了 我就喜欢看这个
I'm fed up of the pair of yer talkin' about the damn thing! It's only a bird!
我养你们这么大就是来说这个的吗！ 只是只小鹰而已！
Anyroad, it's not worth stinkin' threepence!
再说了 它根本就值不了两个钱！
Get off! Get off!
滚开！滚开！
Get out!
滚远点！
Get out! And don't come stinkin' back!
永远别回来！